welcome to meditating with John Breaux
Vicki I'm a cognitive psychologist and a
cognitive scientist at the University of
Toronto I study scientifically and
academically mindfulness meditative
practice contemplative practices moving
mindfulness practices I study related
phenomena but insight flow mystical
experience transformative experience
awakening experience higher states of
consciousness the cultivation of wisdom
in addition I've been practicing the
pasta meditation at a contemplation and
Tai Chi Chuan for over twenty nine years
in an integrated fashion and I've been
teaching those three as well as some
Qigong for almost 20 years so welcome
this is a course Monday's our Dharma
days every Monday I'm teaching in
principle usually do an exercise so you
get a direct experience all
understanding of the principle and then
Tuesday through Friday we do some review
we sit together and after every day at
the end of every day Monday through
Friday
there is a Q&A that Q&A is directed
specifically towards questions around
this practice some of you have been
asking me more general questions like
how does this practice you know compared
to stoic practices or how do I fit this
into a more comprehensive way of life or
what's the relationship between what
we're doing here and the cultivation of
wisdom more broadly you know very
general questions or questions even both
some of my other videos or my my series
awakening from meeting crisis but those
kinds of questions will be having a live
streamed Q&A tomorrow 3 p.m. est for
those of you who are joining us for the
first time you can find links in the
description of this video to previous
videos well you'll find both the
previous sits and the previous lesson
there's a playlist dedicated to just the
previous lessons so you can go and catch
up so you can continue on with us if you
would like alright so I think that's
everything we need to do just get ready
so please get yourself ready into your
posture put your phones on do not
disturb and we will begin what I say
together begin
you
slowly begin to come out of your
practice trying as best you can to
integrate what you cultivated in your
practice with your everyday
consciousness and cognition coming out
of your sit it's part of the properties
so time for a few questions today
could you Olaf
got hooked I if I mispronounce your name
like all the does I find it very very
hard to do the routine and often I do
not get past it within 15 minutes I get
really an agitated monkey brain I try to
do some routing light to reduce the time
yes yeah you can perhaps just right just
go to the center do a little bit of
routing the central line of your head
maybe one or two breaths just opening
right just the opening and then sort of
a melting and draining down to your
heart and then that opening the opening
you're getting with the looking and the
listening just they're opening letting
it flow and then melting and draining
center of your abdomen couple breaths
just opening letting it flow getting
that kind of relaxation that's a
sensitization and stabilization and
opening and melting down to the center
like of your root contact point on the
earth I mean and then opening letting it
flow there and then opening melting
draining sinking into the earth so you
can do that that won't take you as deep
but it will hopefully give you a way of
doing as you say a light version of it
but still nevertheless get you into the
other the relaxation but that's right
both sensitizing
and a stabilization and affords you
finding your flow Andre
hi Andre it's good to see you again what
you were meant to do what do you
remember as myself out of the feeling
like falling asleep or losing
consciousness so one other thing is you
so this is one of the few instances
where you do want to direct your
breathing you want to take some very
deep baby breaths and you want to try
and Riaan
very deeply and your abdomen your heart
all of your torso I don't do that a lot
don't hyperventilate but two or three
because if only miss lis probably cuz
you're getting too little oxygen in so
here if you really if this is really
becoming a challenge right you can't
just sort of open your mind directly
then take some deep breaths and while
you're doing the deep breaths really try
to dive deeply into the flow really get
the flow going in your abdomen and your
heart your shoulders and your torso
don't do that for very long but do that
I also recommend I to think of taking up
a moving mindfulness practice that you
do just before your you sit because that
helps to engage the cerebellum it helps
to oxygenate the blood more and it will
help you to remain more awake while
you're sitting Keira
Kruger if something jarring happens
right before starting should you just
wait until a later time to sit what's my
nervous system has had a chance to calm
down that's a good question that's a
hard question to ask so generally that
that goes with how long you've been
practicing and how deep your practice is
going if it's very jarring I recommend
not trying to sit could you'll just be
replayed replacing it but I recommend
right doing you know two or three
open-eyed two and three open-eyed
following your breaths wherever you are
getting a sense of being centered and
rooted and coming in as much as you can
to the flow feeling within your body
so yes probably if you're you know if
you're relatively nervous
don't go immediately into sitting if
something drawing has just happened but
in in that state where you're right you
wanna you want to
you want to train your brain so that
when you're coming into something
jarring it looks to Center and root and
flow and to open up that soft vigilance
kind of paying attention rather than the
hard focusing so yes probably not not
sit but like I say bring in open eyed
finding your Center you know don't do it
comprehensively just a little bit on
your Center getting that sense of
rootedness getting coming into a flow
state and try to remember what it's like
to pay attention to whatever it is it's
jarring but pay attention with the soft
vigilance as you can come less of a
novice and you're go deeper in your
meditation than you would you would then
sit but if you're a novice that's what I
recommend you do a crema my dreamy you
you you're such a diligent follower of
this practice and I commend you for that
I have meditated for many years and ever
less than 30 minutes it takes me 15
minutes to become still do you suggest
our second meditation and the evening to
be longer if you if you want to say
there it's not that you have to limit
yourself to 50 minutes if remember I
said this is always relative I just may
be 15 because I've taught this for a
long time
and I know what sort of is on average
for people you want to always get in
their zone of proximal development if it
takes you if you need to sit for you
know 30 minutes to get into that zone of
proximal development
then sit for 30 minutes and said twice a
day for 30 minutes if you can
Nick Kennedy fine it good to see you
again can we book in the additional mind
questing directly after our morning sis
yes you can yes you can if you find that
it's remember this is always not this is
never something you nearly endure if you
find that you're getting educated not in
terms of the answers you're getting but
if you're getting educated in the
process of meditative questing then yes
you can do that very much very much so
everyone I want to thank everyone for
joining as always I want to thank my
dear friend and techno mage am are my
beloved son Jason
please subscribe to the channel to be
notified of the next videos you'll also
find on my channel a lot of videos about
mindfulness and flow and insight a
mystical experience and wisdom etc and
also the comprehensive change I believe
our culture is facing facing and
awakening for the meaning crisis please
invite others to this practice to the
sitting point them to the previous
lessons if they want to catch up I'm
trying to help as many people as I can
and it would be great if you helped me
help as many people as I can by reaching
out pointing people to this series to my
channel etc please remember we have the
live Q&A for those more comprehensive
questions that people might have
tomorrow at 3 p.m. est we will in a via
announcing that you can find me on
LinkedIn Facebook and Twitter and there
will also be notifications on YouTube so
we're doing this every weekday morning
from 9:30 est on Mondays our Dharma days
Tuesdays through Fridays or sit and
please remember everybody continuity of
practice is really important if you
honestly can only sit for 5 minutes sit
for 5 minutes take care everyone I'll
see you all tomorrow